Preliminary Guide to the Speech and Hearing Department records, 1950-1989 RG0081
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Speech and Hearing Department records
1950-1989
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
George Washington University. Dept. of Speech
RG0081
0.5 Linear Feet
Materials in this collection include brochures and office files. They range in date from 1950 to 1989.
Restrictions on Access
Series 1 is closed to research for 25 years from date of record creation.
Acquisition Information
Materials acquired through transfers from the Speech and Hearing Department.
Historical Note
Since 2002, the department has been known as Speech and Hearing Science. The department is within the Columbian College of Arts and Sciences (CCAS), and has two graduate programs; one for those who have an undergraduate degree in speech language pathology and one for those who have an undergraduate degree from another field. In addition, the department has a graduate program in Speech-Language Pathology.
As part of the department, the Speech and Hearing Center provides a full range of speech, language, and hearing services for individuals with communicative disorders. The newest and most innovative techniques, materials, and equipment are used. The Center serves persons of all ages, from infants to senior citizens. Counseling is also provided for the family of the communicatively handicapped individual. Faculty and students are also involved in clinical research projects.
As part of the training and service missions of the department, The George Washington University established its Speech and Hearing Center in 1946, to train graduate students to serve those with communication impairments in the metropolitan Washington D.C. area. Certified speech language pathologists and audiologists (both faculty and staff) provide the many hours of direct graduate student supervision necessary to ensure superb training for our students and quality speech language and hearing services to hundreds of clients per year.
Prior to 2002 the department was known as the Speech and Hearing Department (1983-2002), and from 1968-83 it was part of the Speech and Drama Department. From 1965-68 it was known as the Speech and Hearing Clinic, and before that as the Speech Clinic.
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include brochures and office files. They range in date from 1950- to 1989. Parts of this collection are unprocessed. Please see Special Collections staff for assistance.
Collection Organization
Organized in two series Departmental records; and Brochures and application.
Washington (D.C.); George Washington University
- Departmental records, 1966-1989; RG0081 Series 1; 0.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains departmental records. These materials date from 1988-89.
  Formerly ACC#47
  This series is unprocessed, please ask staff for assistance.
  - Name change, 1966-1986 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Department description, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - ESB Annual Report, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Reaccreditation Application, 1977-1983 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - ETB Annual Report, 1975-1981 (Box 2, Folder 6-11)
  - Brochures and flyers, 1972-1980 (Box 2, Folder 12-15)
- Brochures and application, 1950; RG0081 Series 2; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series contains brochures and an application from 1950. The materials are about the Speech and Hearing Center and the Speech Pathology and Audiology program.
  Formerly vertical files.
  - Speech and Hearing Center, 1966-06/29/1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Summer Sessions--Advance Registration Program (SAPR), 1966-06/29/1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)